理发店
他们输了65场比赛
They lose 65 games
结果只拿到了4号签
only to end up with the fourth pick in the draft.
老爹理发店
他们是他妈故意输球的吗
Did they tank that shit on purpose?
自己看看墙上写了啥  老爹
Read the words, Pop. Right there on the wall.
他说得对  亨利  虽然我不愿承认
Brother's got a point, Henry, much as I hate to admit that.
是啊  拿钱
That's right. Pay up.
你说得对  我不该爆粗口
You're right, you're right. I shouldn't have cursed.
粗口罚钱罐
-我的错  朗尼  -没事  老爹
- My bad, Lonnie. - It's okay, Pop.
他们今年的记录是什么
What's their record this year, anyway, like?
17胜  65负
17 and 65.
他们选的那个俄罗斯小子  最好够厉害
You know that Russian kid they drafted? He better be good.
他是拉脱维亚的
He's Latvian.
他们应该开了菲尔·杰克逊
What they need to do is fire Phil Jackson.
等等  菲尔·杰克逊已经不打了
Wait a minute, Phil Jackson ain't out there playing no more.
菲尔·杰克逊没那么厉害啦  B
Phil Jackson overrated, B.
队里有乔丹和科比  谁都能拿冠军
Anybody can win with Jordan and Kobe.
菲尔又不是帕特·莱利
Phil ain't no Pat Riley.
又提莱利
Aw, Riley, again?
-嗯  -又来了
- Yeah. - Here we go.
帕西诺
I mean, Pacino...
我明白那个白人为什么在你的免费剪名单上
Now, I get why that white boy makes your free haircut list.
默罕默德·阿里  尼尔森·曼德拉  理查德·朗德垂  迈克尔·乔丹  艾尔·帕西诺  帕特·莱利  不需要付钱  其他人必须付  不赊账
《教父》和《疤面煞星》
The Godfather and Scarface
确保了他永远能在贫民区畅行无阻
guaranteed that man an eternal ghetto pass.
还有《情枭的黎明》
Carlito's Way, too.
-但是帕特·莱利  -嗯
- But Pat Riley? - Yeah.
为什么这家店这么喜欢帕特·莱利
Why does Pat Riley get so much love in this shop?
嗯  就连那臭小子德雷克·菲舍的
Right. Even punk-ass Derek Fisher
总冠军戒指都比帕特·莱利多
got more rings than Pat Riley.
知道啦
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
帕特·莱利当教练时  尼克斯队打得够血性
'Cause the Knicks played like men when Pat Riley was head coach.
奥克利和尤因在内线势不可挡
Oakley and Ewing went hard in the paint.
加上安东尼·梅森和约翰·斯塔克斯
Plus Anthony Mason and John Starks?
他们的外线突破能要你的命
Drive the lane, you might go home in a body bag.
说得好
All right, now I heard that.
后来图片分享
Later with all that Instagramming,
"兄弟篮球"那套扯淡
"Let's all max contract on the same team together" bullcrap
如今成了主流
passing as competition nowadays.
帕特·莱利当上迈阿密热火队总经理后
Didn't Pat Riley sign those Instagram dudes down in Miami
不是签了图片分享上的人吗
when he became the GM?
或许吧
Maybe.
但詹姆斯确实很强  他的球技无可挑剔
But King James is the truth. LeBron can ball.
给钱  卢克  你说"扯淡"了
Now pay up, Luke. You said "bullcrap."
"扯淡"不算粗口  我不爆粗口
"Bullcrap" ain't a curse, man. I don't curse.
"我不爆粗口"
"I don't curse."
你也不理发  黑鬼
You don't cut hair either, negro.
真的  你究竟在这儿做什么啊
Like, really, what do you do up in here, bruh?
我扫头发  沙米克
I sweep hair, Shameek.
我还拖地  我还洗毛巾
I also mop, I wash the towels,
我还把那块玻璃窗擦得一尘不染
and I make sure that plate glass window stays spotless.
这叫工作  你是永远不会理解的
It's called work. Something you would never understand.
少年队加油
这可是《灌篮》
Slam Magazine...
好多教练靠这玩意选人呢  小子
Coaches used to live up in this piece, son.
凯文·奥利的头还是老爹给剪的
Kevin Ollie got a shape-up right there from Pop's.
皮蒂诺也是
Pitino, too.
时髦  拉风  那是我的范儿
Stylin' and profilin', that's my work.
-懂了吧  -嗯  让他知道
- See what I'm sayin'? Yeah? - Yeah. Tell him.
真的
For real?
篮球教练
道格·里弗斯找你了吗  沙米克
Doc Rivers, uh, call you yet, Shameek?
好了  别惹事
Whoa, all right. Play nice.
-你连头都剪不起  -告诉你
- You can't even afford a haircut. - Hey, you know what?
-我受够了...  -什么
- I'm about sick and tired of... - What?
你受够了什么
You sick and tired of what?
受够了尼克斯队总输球
About sick and tired of the Knicks losin' all the time, man!
那里还有头发
You got some hair, too, right there.
-我还没完事呢  -你完了
- I'm not finished. - Yes, you are.
-律师  -别触我霉头  老爹
- Hey, Counselor. - Aw, don't jinx me, Pop.
我还没通过律师考试呢
I haven't even passed the bar yet.
你会的
Oh, you will.
朗尼  你今晚有课  走吧
Lonnie, you got Kumon tonight. Let's go.
走  孩子  听妈妈的话
Come on, boy, you heard your mama.
走吧
Let's get moving.
别逼我再说一遍
Don't make me repeat myself.
卢克
Hey, Luke.
你什么时候下班
What time you get off?
这份工作结束后我还得马上赶去做另一份
I got another job I go to right after I leave this one.
黑人工作  这没什么不对
Black man working. Ain't nothing wrong with that.
我们至少该找时间喝杯咖啡
Well, we should at least try to get some coffee some time.
或许你有一日会需要律师
Maybe you'll need a lawyer one day.
希望你到时有名片了
Hopefully, you'll have some cards by then.
一定替我向贝茜带好
Be sure and tell Bessie I said hey.
我会的
I will.
为什么那样一个拿公文包的美女
How's a woman that fine with a briefcase
会对一个拿扫帚的男人投怀送抱
gonna throw it at a brother with a broom?
不懂了吧  小子
That's what you don't get, youngin.
全看你有没有魅力了
Either you have it or you don't.
我当然有了
Oh, I know I got it.
该死
Shit.
看到墙上的字了吗
See the words... right there on the wall.
不许说粗话
-给钱  -得了  老爹
- Pay up. - Come on, Pop.
你又来了
Huh, there you go again.
我出狱后戒了一切
I shook everything else after I got out.
香烟  偏执
Cigarettes, paranoia...
但踱步
But the pacing?
我也会这样
I do it, too.
又是因为瑞瓦吗
Reva again?
永远是
Reva always.
已经过了够久了
Look, it's been long enough.
给帕蒂打电话吧  她是个好女人
Give Patty a call. She's a good woman.
我不怎么喝咖啡
I don't drink coffee much.
我觉得她也是
I don't think she does either.
就像她说的  "这没什么不对"
Like she said, "Ain't nothing wrong with that."
等我准备好  自然就准备好了
When I'm ready, I'm ready.
但你迟早会想来杯温暖黝黑的东西
But you'll want a cup of something hot and dark sooner or later...
金钟铁罩先生
Mr. Bulletproof.
你又乱起外号了  老爹
There you go with the nicknames, Pop.
你说你的救生圈炮友
You said your rebound chick
拿一把猎枪近距离
took a shotgun at point-blank range...
抵住了你的下巴
pointed it under your chin,
然后开了枪
and pulled the trigger.
我现在还偶尔头疼呢
I still get the occasional headache.
对你来说不是事  神力侠
Not a problem for you, Power Man.
我喜欢看你做那种事
I love it when you do stuff like that.
我就是觉得  你该出去帮助大家
You should be out there helping people, that's all,
像城里其他那些人
like them other fellas downtown.
瑞瓦以前也这么说
Reva used to say the same thing.
她是对的
Yeah, well, she was right.
你就从不想想你本可以帮助的人吗
You don't ever think about all the people you could help?
你该有点野心
You should be more ambitious.
如果我的野心就是扫扫头发
What if my ambition is to sweep hair...
洗洗盘子
wash dishes...
求别人不打扰呢
and be left the hell alone?
那就浪费了
Well, that would be a waste.
你以为这一切是我想要的吗
You think I asked for any of this?
我被陷害  被打
I was framed, beaten...
像只热带鱼似的被关起来观察
and put in some tank like an exotic fish.
出来时
Came out with...
就有了能力
abilities.
救了你一命
Saved your life.
不如说是毁了我的生活
More like ruined it.
瑞瓦死了
Reva's dead.
我成了逃犯
I'm a fugitive.
那又如何
So?
听我一句  伙计
Take my advice, brother.
过去只是过去
The past is the past.
生活唯一要紧的方向就是前方
And the only direction in life that matters is forward.
绝不是后方
Never backwards.
我只想过一天
I'm just living my life...
是一天
day to day.
你走路看着点
Why don't you watch where you going, man?
拿枪做什么  奇科
What's the gun for, Chico?
你是叫维尔弗雷多·迪亚兹吗
Is your name Wilfredo Diaz?
因为此人在我九岁时抛弃了我妈
'Cause he walked out on me and moms when I was nine.
我那时不需要爸爸  现在也不需要
I ain't need a daddy then and I don't need one now.
-去拿钱吧  -好
- Let's get this money. - Yeah.
老爹  我得走了  要迟了
Hey, Pop, I gotta go. I'm runnin' late.
如果我不是拿现金支付你薪水
Look, if I wasn't paying you in cash,
我还能给你更多钱的
I could be paying you more.
那你也不用打两份工了
You wouldn't have to be workin' two jobs.
我得做我该做的
I gotta do what I gotta do.
永远向前
Always forward.
向前  永远
Forward. Always.
伙计
Hey, yo, my man, my man.
全是高清的  都在这儿了
All HD. Got it right here.
还有蓝光  我就是这么棒棒哒
Blu-ray, too, 'cause I'm nice like that.
1吉吉倩倩
2大葱大圣
5菲菲查查事件影像
3SpohyAvis
4SpohyAvis
托尼·斯塔克  拿锤子的金发大块头
Tony Stark, the big blonde dude with the hammer,
拿盾的那个老头
the old dude with the shield,
绿怪物  而且我不是指芬威球场
the green monster, and I don't mean Fenway.
没有别人有比我更清晰的
You can't get better raw footage of the incident
事件原片了
anywhere else than right here.
卢克
Hey, Luke.
每次都被你发现
Every time.
是消毒水  老远就闻到了
It's the bleach. I can smell it from around the corner.
老爹又让你洗毛巾了
Pop has got you washing towels again, huh?
嗯  我替你留了本《纽约客》
Yeah, I took a New Yorker off the top for you.
但不知道封面是什么
Can't tell you what's on the cover, though.
希望你凑到房租给康妮了
Hey, I hope you got Connie's rent money.
她要气坏了
She's on the warpath.
谢谢  奥利
Thanks, Ollie.
迟了十天  凯奇先生  我需要收房租了
Ten days late, Mr. Cage. I need my rent money.
吉思康妮中餐馆
给
Here.
三百  不够
I count $300. Not enough.
让我去上班好把其余的挣到
Let me go to work and get the rest.
今晚交齐
Tonight.
哈莱姆
帮个忙  需要个酒保  但丁病了
I need a favor. Short one bartender. Dante's sick.
你拿来说好的现金了吗
You got the cash you promised me?
-周末的  -拜托  内特
- End of the week. - Come on, Nate.
小费你可以自己留着
You can keep all your tips out there, okay?
你多久没调酒了
When was the last time you made drinks?
我会的
I know the drill.
好吧  收拾一下
Okay, okay. Clean up.
穿上衬衫  外套  斯托克斯先生要求高
Put a shirt and jacket on. Mr. Stokes has standards.
这倒不体现在工资上
Though you can't tell by what he pays.
什么
Excuse me?
拉斐尔·沙狄克
Raphael Saadiq.
他现场表现就像你说的那么好
He's as good live as you said he was.
比我说得还好
Even better.
你不觉得很了不起吗
So you're not impressed by all this?
我一直为你骄傲
I've always been proud of you.
梅布尔妈妈死时  这地方就是蟑螂窝
This place was a roach trap by the time Mama Mabel died.
现在再看看
Now look at it.
哈莱姆的天堂  可以说是新棉花酒吧了
Harlem's Paradise. May as well be the new Cotton Club.
那我今晚就不该来
Then I shouldn't be up in here tonight.
好吧
Well...
议员女士
Madam Councilwoman...
科隆健身房愿意给我一笔慷慨的捐助
Colon's Gym is ready to make a sizable donation to my pocket...
也资助你的房地产项目
and your real estate project.
有时候得面对面谈
Sometimes you need a face-to-face.
科隆健身房
"Colon's Gym"?
那个二流毒贩
Is that what that two-bit drug dealer
就是这么写报税单的
is puttin' on his tax returns?
你为何要在他身上浪费时间
Why do you even waste time with him?
政界才有权力  康奈尔
Politics is where the power is, Cornell.
别管其他的了
Forget about all this other noise.
我的生意让你兴旺
My noise keeps you flush.
那番"让哈莱姆黑下去"的
All that "keep Harlem black"
唬人把戏虽然让你赢得重选
rack-a-bully-ack might get you re-elected.
-可不是  -但等烟幕弹散去
- Damn skippy. - But when the smoke clears...
是我这样的黑鬼允许你维持下去
it's niggas like me that let you hold on to what you got.
你知道我讨厌那个词
You know I despise that word.
我知道
I know.
人们很容易低估黑鬼
It's easy to underestimate a nigga.
你总能打他们个措手不及
They never see you coming.
-那是什么  -大都市
- What's that? - It's a cosmo.
你的外套有点小
Your jacket's a little small.
你的裙子也是
So is your dress.
说得对
Touché.
-康奈尔  伙计  -香槟
- Cornell, my man. - Champagne.
-好啊  -议员女士
- All right. - Councilwoman.
-你们在庆祝什么  -成功
- What are you two celebrating? - Success.
这份合作早该展开了
Partnership that should have happened a long time ago, had...
如果当初我叔叔和你哥哥得逞了的话
my uncle and your brother had their way.
皮特叔叔是好人
Uncle Pete was good people.
萨尔瓦多非常喜欢皮特
Salvador really liked Pete.
不客气
Anytime.
-在找什么吗  -没有
- Lookin' for somethin'? - No.
沙狄克还那么厉害
Saadiq's still got it.
《石滚》这张专辑真不错
Stone Rollin' was a dope album.
专辑  这下我知道你是个老人家了
"Album"? Now I know you're an old head.
你也不是什么小鲜肉啊  小子
You ain't no spring chicken neither, sucker.
说得对
Touché.
好了  是这么回事吗
All right. So let me get this straight.
我给你堂亲捐钱
I give your cousin a contribution
就等于得到一张免狱金牌
and it's like a get out of jail free card for me, right?
这是值得庆祝
That's something to celebrate.
不  我不做那种事
No, I don't do that.
我呢
See, me...
等事情了结了才会庆祝
I celebrate when things are finished.
而不是在才开始时庆祝
Not when it's just starting.
听他的
Listen to him.
这不值得庆祝
This is nothing to celebrate.
你看到菲斯克的下场了
You saw what happened to Fisk.
你俩根本不该被看到在一起
You two shouldn't even be seen together...
更别说还带上我了
let alone having me all up in the Kool-Aid.
但你反正也来了  那肯定是有道理的
But you're here anyway. Something must be right about it.
否则  你不同意也不会给我预付款了
Otherwise, you wouldn't have fronted me if you didn't agree.
我对我们家族的遗产不抱幻想
I have no illusions about our family's legacy.
但你现在又把合法的钱变非法了
But you are now turning legitimate money illegal all over again.
怎么非法了
What's illegal about it?
我们的产品是受《宪法》保护的
Our product is protected by the Constitution.
但你来找我是因为信任我  多明戈
But you came to me because you trust me, Domingo.
在你这行里
In your business,
人们对我的产品就像鱼儿需要水一样
people need my product like a fish needs water.
他上哪都能买水
He can buy his water anywhere.
我卖的是纯的
What I sell is pure.
这种东西能在战舰上炸个洞
This the kind of shit that could blow a hole in a battleship.
但又轻得可以拿在手里
But it's light enough to hold in your hand.
相信我  多明戈
Trust me, Domingo.
这东西能炸得天光亮
You can brighten someone's day permanently with this shit.
顶级的货
Top of the line.
精华中的精华
The crème de la crème.
《钢铁侠2》中的军火商
A级  军用  贾斯汀·汉默级别的东西
This that grade A, military, Justin Hammer-level shit.
汉默
每箱10万  十箱一百万
A hundred large per case. Ten cases, a cool mil.
批发  崭新崭新的
Wholesale. Brand spanking new.
没有序列号  我的人就是有这本事
No serial numbers... because my connect is nice like that.
你的人是谁
Who's your connect?
他确有其人  而且货存量很足
He's real and his inventory runs deep.
-就这样  -是的
- So that's it. - That's it.
-就这么简单  -从没有什么是简单的
- Easy-peasy. - Nothing's ever that easy.
他们打来确认之后呢
So what happens after they call to confirm?
皆大欢喜  各回各家
Everyone walks away happy.
不是只有快递能把货送到
UPS ain't the only brown that delivers.
好伙计
My man.
小子  这就对了
Yeah, kid. That's what I'm talkin' about.
瞧见了吗  我去
Yo, you see this? Damn!
你不该杀人的  伙计
You wasn't supposed to kill nobody, man!
我必须动手  但丁  出了岔子  我的错
I had to make a move, Dante. Shit went left. My bad.
天呐  该死  天呐
Oh, my God. Oh, fuck. God.
闭嘴  奇科  别逼我拿你的裤头堵你的嘴
Shut up, Chico, before I gag you with your panties.
你们看见这钱了吗  B
Yo, y'all see this money, B?
就像好莱坞电影似的
Yo, this shit is like some Hollywood shit for real.
沙米克  我怎么办  他们会知道是我的
Shameek, what am I gonna do? They're gonna know it was me.
B  这里有一百万呢
B, there's, like, a million dollars right here.
水腹蛇在酒吧总看不起我
Cottonmouth always lookin' down at me at the bar.
他会发现我不见了  会知道这是监守自盗
He's gonna know I'm gone. They gonna know it was a inside job.
你说得对
You right.
你做了什么
What'd you do?
这玩意好用
Yo, shit works.
这玩意好用  奇科
Yo, this shit works, Chico.
但丁肯定会告密的
Dante would have snitched.
你看到他多害怕了吗
You see... you see how shook he was?
拜托  伙计  我...
Come on, man. I ain't...
我不会把钱分三份的
Ain't no way I'm splitting that shit three ways no how, man.
但丁是我们的一员  B  那是但丁啊
Dante was crew, B. That's Dante!
我做了个决定  这下我有钱了
Yo, I made a decision. I'm gonna be rich.
我们走吧
Let's go.
走吧  走
Let's go! Come on!
你是候补  还是不够格
So you're a bench-warmer? Or did you miss the cut?
什么
Excuse me?
我以为你是...他的人
I just figured you were... one of his.
水腹蛇的什么
One of Cottonmouth's?
听说他讨厌那个名字
I hear he hates that name.
-斯托克斯先生  -水腹蛇的...
- Mr. Stokes'-- - Cottonmouth's...
模特
Models.
你为什么那么想
What makes you assume that?
你很美  但是...
You're beautiful. But...
但是什么
But what?
你比他一般好的那口要老点
You're a little older than he usually likes them.
你今晚是别想要小费了
Yeah, you're definitely not getting a tip tonight.
我还没说完呢
But I'm not finished.
蠢男人才喜欢小姑娘
Dumb men like little girls.
我
Me?
我考虑女人
I ponder a woman.
你
Why don't you...
再给我调杯大都市吧
ponder me another cosmo?
卢克
Luke.
坎迪斯
Hey, Candace.
你被升职了
You got promoted?
但丁病了
Dante's out sick.
你没事吧
You okay?
7号桌要六瓶黑桃A
Table seven wants six bottles of Ace of Spades.
我需要你帮我端上去
I need you to help me carry them up.
我不想一个人上去
I don't like being up there by myself.
我就来  稍等
I'm right behind you. Give me a second.
我回来前
Why don't you...
你想想这个吧
ponder that 'til I get back.
你块头真大
You're a big one, eh?
他的外套太小了
He's wearing a little jacket.
没见过你当酒保
Haven't seen you behind the bar.
但丁呢
Where's Dante?
请病假了吧
Called in sick, I guess.
你想要份工作吗
You want a job?
我能找到更适合你这块头的人的工作
I can find something more suitable for a man your size.
薪水也更好
Better paying, too.
你拿过枪吗
You ever carried a gun?
没有
No.
不用了  谢谢
I'm good. Thanks.
喂
Yeah?
该死  妈的
Shit. Fuck.
你想赶上公车  得步行去
You got to walk over to Adam Clayton Powell
亚当·克雷顿·鲍威尔街
if you wanna catch the bus.
优步
Uber?
-你是想叫车  是吗  -你是什么人
- That's what you were gonna press, right? - What are you?
-警察吗  -不是
- A cop? - No.
你似乎有些冷
You just look cold.
如果你找斯托克斯先生  他刚走
If you're looking for Mr. Stokes, he just left.
谁
Who?
黑色凯迪拉克
Black Escalade.
贴了黑色车窗膜
Tinted windows.
你不用去哪吗
Don't you have... somewhere you need to be?
嗯
Yeah.
回家
Home.
刚下班
Just got off.
恭喜
Congratulations.
想去喝杯咖啡吗
You wanna go grab a coffee?
我不喜欢咖啡
I don't like coffee.
我也是
Neither do I.
什么时候
When?
我这就去
I'm on my way in.
你说梦话
You talk in your sleep.
我说什么了
What was I saying?
沙兹  科曼奇
Shades? Comanche?
我得去工作了
The job is calling me in.
我能回头打给你吗
Can I call you later?
那你得有我的电话号码
You'd need my phone number for that.
我知道你在哪工作
I know where you work.
我会去找你
I'll find you.
你做什么的来着
What is it you do again?
审计员
I'm an auditor.
那是干什么的
What's that?
简单说  我看财务账簿
Basically, I look at the financial books.
确保一切都好
Make sure everything's on the up and up.
为此需要穿短裙吗
And you need a short dress for that?
有时候得融入大家嘛
Sometimes you got to blend in.
不可能
Impossible.
你在哪都会鹤立鸡群
You stand out in any room you're in.
多米尼加人  古巴人
Dominicans? Cubans?
波多黎各人
Puerto Ricans.
那不是上周的事吗
Thought that parade was last week.
谁记得住啊
Who can keep track?
你觉得他是想打给谁
Who do you think this guy was trying to call?
捉鬼敢死队
Ghostbusters.
他可以笑  你不可以
He can laugh. You can't.
贝利  你好吗
Hey, Bailey. How you doing?
天气美好  又能坐办公室  有什么不好的
It's another beautiful day at the office. What's not to love?
你可别唱起来了
Don't you start singing show tunes on me.
该死
Oh, shit.
但丁·查普曼
Dante Chapman.
你认识他
You know him?
我认识他妈妈
I know his mama.
当然不会是监守自盗
Of course it wasn't a inside job.
我们也死了人
We had people die, too.
东西不在我这儿
Look... I don't have the stuff.
我们得当面谈
We need to talk about this in person.
我的话依然有效力
My word is still my bond.
喂
Hello?
多明戈吗
That's Domingo?
怎么了
Yo, what's up?
你不够格知道
It's above your pay grade.
什么
What?
告诉你的人出了什么事  康奈尔
Tell your man what's going on, Cornell.
地方不错
Nice digs.
比梅布尔妈妈经营时还好
Even nicer than when Mama Mabel ran it.
沙兹
Shades.
你什么时候回来的
When'd you come home?
有一阵了
Ooh, a while ago.
海门监狱不赖
Seagate wasn't shit.
我能为你做什么
So... what can I do for you?
是反过来
It's the other way around.
你们昨晚遇袭了
Y'all got hit last night.
响尾蛇给你们的
That expensive, exclusive,
昂贵  少见  难找的武器
hard-to-get hardware that Diamondback gave you
现在在警方证据室
is in a police evidence lockup.
多明戈和他的人
And the money... that Domingo
该给你的钱
and his crew were supposed to give you...
不见了
is gone.
我现在是响尾蛇的人  你知道吧
I'm with Diamondback now. You knew that, right?
告诉响尾蛇  该...
Well, tell Diamondback, it's about time--
是响尾蛇要告诉你
Diamondback tells you.
我是他的最大卖家
I'm his number one seller.
我不是来惩罚你的
I ain't here to spank you.
但我得看着你的眼睛
But I do need to look you in your eyes...
是监守自盗吗
Was it an inside job?
不是
No.
绝对不是
Hell no.
我也需要那笔钱
I needed that money, too.
这种信任是很难建立的
It took forever to build up that kind of trust.
我们是来帮你稳住阵脚的
We're here to get you back on your feet.
听你安排
Whatever you need.
著名黑人盲人音乐家
"我们"是谁  你个假冒雷·查尔斯
Who is "we," you fake-ass Ray Charles?
我会挺你的  B
I got your back, B.
就像以前那样
Just like back in the day.
别管以前了
Forget about back in the day.
为什么感觉像是接管
Why is this feeling like a takeover?
不是的
It's not.
如果是
If it was...
响尾蛇会迅雷不及掩耳的
you would never even see Diamondback comin'.
他希望你赢
He wants you to win.
我能做什么
How can I help?
完蛋了
但丁是我看大的孩子  奇科也是
Dante was one of my kids. So was Chico.
还有沙米克
And Shameek, too.
就像在那边玩的孩子
Just like those kids playing over there.
就得这样哄他们信任你
You know, that's how you get 'em on your side.
扫扫头发  跑跑腿
Sweepin' up hair. Runnin' errands.
让他们在这儿玩  打游戏
Lettin' 'em hang out, play video games.
什么都比
Anything is better than
外面世界等着他们的强
what's waiting for them out there on the street.
他们想要条出路
They want a way out...
但他们太骄傲  不愿求助
but they have too much pride to ask for help.
所以你得哄他们上道
So you gotta Jedi mind-trick them into something.
人人都有枪  人人都没爸
Everyone has a gun. No one has a father.
说得是
Ain't that the truth.
你确定是他们干的
You sure they did it?
事发半小时后大家开始给我打电话
People started callin' me half an hour after it happened.
沙米克一直是个火花塞
Shameek has always been the spark plug.
奇科  是跟屁虫
And Chico... A follower.
我不敢相信他俩
I just can't believe that either one of them...
会调过头来
would just turn around...
杀了但丁
and kill... Dante.
你没发现他俩有什么不对劲吧
You didn't see anything going on with either one of 'em, did you?
没有
No.
生死都是你的选择
You live and die by your choices.
这是哈莱姆的花园  就是这么回事
This is Harlem's garden. That's what's happening here.
你们能让这个社区...
You are the ones that are gonna keep this community--
真是...天呐  这是玛丽索  亲爱的
Where have-- Oh, God. This is Marisol. Baby--
天呐  从她出生就认识她了
Oh, my God, known her since she was first born.
你来改变哈莱姆了
And here you are upturnin' Harlem around.
我真为你骄傲
I'm so proud of you.
我今早看见你赶公车了
I saw you running for the bus this mornin'.
好了  亲爱的
All right, darling.
很高兴你来了  亲爱的
I'm happy you made it, darling.
三个后就别再给他了
Cut him off at three.
我认识这个小伙儿  他能吃五个汉堡
I know this young brother. He'll eat five hamburgers.
我见过你那么做
I've seen you do it.
哈莱姆欢迎每个人  所有人
Now, Harlem is a community that welcomes everyone. All people.
但同时
But at the same time,
黑人作家  活动家
自朗斯顿·休斯
since the days of Langston Hughes,
黑人民权领袖
马尔科姆·艾克斯
Malcolm X,
黑人女作家
佐拉·尼尔·赫斯顿
Zora Neale Hurston,
黑人音乐家
艾灵顿公爵的时代起
Duke Ellington,
哈莱姆就是美国黑人界的瑰宝
Harlem has been the jewel of black America.
它永远象征着
It's a perpetual symbol of...
希望  繁荣和卓越
of hope and prosperity and excellence.
黑人的命想得到尊重
For black lives to matter,
黑人历史和黑人所有权就都得得到尊重
black history and black ownership must also matter.
我为克里斯珀斯·阿塔克斯大楼制定的多层面计划
Now, my multifaceted plan for the Crispus Attucks Complex
也是为了给新一代带来希望
is just yet another way to bring hope to a new generation,
孕育令哈莱姆闻名的
to incubate the kind of innovation and creativity
创新  创造和进步
and progress that Harlem's famous for.
再次感谢您抽时间  议员女士
Thank you again for your time, Madam Councilwoman.
梅根  哈莱姆永远欢迎你
Oh, Megan, you're always welcome in Harlem.
-好  -好  亲爱的
- All right. - All right, darling.
你们得退后
Y'all need to fall the hell back.
奇普  给她点空间
Zip, give her some space.
我不喜欢暴徒
I don't like the thugs.
-你需要他们做安保  -他们让人害怕
- You need them for security. - Mmm, they scare people.
他们发传单  拿到献金  礼物
They pass out flyers, get contributions, tributes.
就像在牙买加  是吧
Just like in Jamaica, you know?
我们不是牙买加人  康奈尔
Yeah, well, we ain't Jamaican, Cornell.
你不该来  我们不能被拍到在一起
You shouldn't be here. We don't need to be photographed together.
为什么
Why?
你以我为耻吗
You ashamed of me?
真伤人  玛莉娅
That hurts, Mariah.
托尼
Tony.
给我们点时间
Will you give us a moment?
我需要尽快拿到你承诺的钱
I need the money you promised me ASAP.
你要钱啊
Now you want the money?
我用了联邦拨款和可避税的献金
I used federal grant and tax-deductible donation money
帮你建成了夜店
to complete construction on your club
以促成那宗刚刚完蛋的交易
and to facilitate that meticulous deal that just fell apart.
我拿不到钱  就会被审计
I don't get the money, I'm facing an audit.
我们都得进监狱
We all go to jail.
会拿到的
It'll be there.
昨晚在废车场里发生了什么
What happened at the junkyard last night?
你身后戴墨镜的那个人是谁
And who's the dude in the sunglasses behind you?
他也是要钱的吗
Is he after the money, too?
你到底是要不要听全部细节  堂亲
Either you want the details, cuz, or you don't.
我猜也是
That's what I thought.
怎么样
What's the word?
但丁临死前说的话都证实了
Confirmation of what Dante told us while he was dying.
他的朋友
His friends,
在拉克夏季联赛为你队打球的
the one that play on your summer league team at the Rucker,
偷了你的货
jacked your shit.
沙米克和奇科
Shameek and Chico.
有人领悬赏吗
Any bites yet?
没有
No.
悬赏翻倍
Double down.
找到那俩蠢货有两万块
Twenty large to find those fools.
托尼  激情正在给他跳舞呢
Tone, Passion is twerking for him right now.
他暂时不会离开的  有那样的美臀冲着他呢
He ain't going nowhere soon. Not with all that ass in his face.
你想要我把他留住  得给我钱
You want me to keep him here, you need to pay me.
伙计  知道几点了吗
Hey, yo, my man. You know what time it is?
8点15
8:15.
坚持哈莱姆
Stay Harlem.
黑人精神
Stay black.
新哈莱姆复兴
-伙计  -别拉我
- Hey, man. - Watch your hands.
你得给我钱
You need to pay me.
我私下给你钱
I'm paying you under the table,
所以我什么时候想给你钱就什么时候给
which means I'll pay you whenever I goddamn feel like it.
你担心什么
What you worried about?
我不担心  我就是没见过水腹蛇
I'm not worried. I just never met Cottonmouth before, that's all.
是斯托克斯先生
Mr. Stokes.
记住了  千万别说水腹蛇
Mr. Stokes. That's important. Never Cottonmouth.
好吧  我的错
All right, okay, my bad.
但丁出事后  我们严阵以待
After what happened with Dante, we circling the wagons.
他们想找我们麻烦  B
They after us, B.
谁
Who?
黑鬼  是谁不要紧
Nigga, it don't matter who.
斯托克斯先生要我亲自看看你好不好
Mr. Stokes wanted me to check on you... personally.
你干什么呢  快来
Yo, what you doin'? Come on.
沙兹
Shades.
喜欢我的声名狼藉先生照片吗
You like my Biggie photo?
我也喜欢
Me, too.
知道你看到它时会被什么吸引住吗
You know what draws your eye when you look at that?
王冠
The crown.
知道为什么吗
Wanna know why?
因为每个人都想当国王
'Cause everybody wants to be the king.
我像扇个小婊子似的打你
I slapped you like a little bitch.
我不会对女人动拳头的
I'm not the kind of man to use a closed fist on a woman.
我的钱呢
Where's my money?
我没...
I... I didn't--
比贼更讨厌的就是撒谎的人
Only thing worse than a thief is a damn liar.
我的
Where's... my...
钱呢
money?
你没杀死但丁  他打给了托尼
You left Dante alive. He called Tone.
他临死前把你和你朋友说出来了
And with his dying words, gave up you and your homeboy.
我们拿到了你的钱
We got your money.
告诉我们奇科在哪  我们好把剩下的钱拿来
Now you're gonna tell us where Chico is so we can get the rest.
嗯  谢谢
Yeah. Thank you.
现在我可以像打男人那样打你了
Now I can hit you like a man.
不
No--
带他出去
Get his ass out of here.
去把我的钱拿回来
And go fetch my money.
他没认出你
He didn't recognize you.
隐形人
孤单不会消失  尤其在海门监狱这样的地方
Loneliness never goes away, especially in places like Seagate.
如果你不跟人交朋友
If you don't make attempts to befriend someone...
孤单一定会吞噬你
loneliness is guaranteed to... eat you alive.
我没事
I'm clear.
我很专注
I'm focused.
我保证  亲爱的
I promise, baby...
我准备好了
I'm ready.
沙米克·史密斯
Shameek Smith...
从在他口袋里找到的东西来看
based on what they found in his pockets.
得靠牙科记录确认他身份了
We'll need dental to confirm ID.
他的脸被打烂了
His face is jacked.
是被弃尸于此的
They definitely dumped him here.
在别处被杀的
They got him somewhere else.
他像是被车撞了
Looks like he got hit by a truck.
是啊
Yeah.
有两个拳头的车
A truck with two fists.
本杰明·富兰克林说
You know, Benjamin Franklin said,
三个人若想保住一个秘密
"The only way that three people can keep a secret
其中两人就得死
is if two of 'em are dead."
先是但丁  现在又是沙米克  只剩奇科了
First Dante, now Shameek. Chico's the last man standing.
本杰明·富兰克林
Benjamin Franklin...
他不是在暴雨里放风筝时把自己电到了吗
Didn't he electrocute himself flying a kite in a rainstorm?
别拿那个蠢货的话当依据
I wouldn't base any theories on that fool.
本杰明·富兰克林可印在一百美元上呢  斯卡夫
Benjamin Franklin is on the $100 bill, Scarfe.
那又如何  他不是总统
So? He wasn't a president.
那就更厉害了  别看扁了他嘛
That's even more impressive. Come on, give the man some credit.
你觉得是奇科杀了沙米克吗
Well... So you think Chico did this to Shameek?
奇科撑死了不到70公斤吧
Chico is what? A buck 50 soaking wet?
但找不到他也不能确认
But we won't know for sure until we find him.
你说你去夜店当晚  但丁没去做酒保
You said Dante wasn't bartendin' the night you were at the club.
是的
No.
你跟当晚替他班的人说话了吗
Well, did you talk to the guy that replaced him that night?
我没怎么跟他说过话
I barely talked to the guy.
我就是点了酒
I mean... all I did was order drinks.
可能有什么规律  我们忽略了什么
Well, maybe there's some pattern, somethin' we're missin'.
我们得去找那人问话
We need to go talk to that guy.
这根本是浪费时间
That sounds like a complete waste of time.
是有这可能
That's entirely possible.
但值得一试
But it's worth a shot.
好吧
All right.
你来这国家多久了
You've been in this country for how long?
你还...不会说英语吗
And you still... can't speak English?
我的英语很好
My English is just fine.
向玛莉娅·迪拉德表示一下
Show Mariah Dillard some love.
捐钱  我们就走
Contribute and we'll go away.
是为了家庭
It's a family thing.
这餐馆是我的
I own this restaurant.
这栋楼是我父亲的
My father owned this building.
告诉玛莉娅·迪拉德  我不会给她的大楼捐钱
Tell Mariah Dillard I am not contributing to her complex.
我们给她投过票  给过她钱
We voted for her and gave her money before.
我尊重斯托克斯先生
And I respect Mr. Stokes.
但今后不会了
But no. No more.
我不能
I can't.
给我们钱
Give us... the money.
我不喜欢你的语气
I don't like your tone.
你说什么
Excuse me?
你很失敬  没这必要
You're being disrespectful. It's unnecessary.
少管闲事  大块头
You need to step off, Mayweather.
你想做什么
I mean, what you think you gonna do, man?
我觉得  他以为自己能干一架
I think he think he gonna bring it.
我能
I can.
但不能放手打  否则会要了你们的命
Not the way I want to. I'd kill you.
我喜欢这小子  艾莫斯
I like this cat. Yo, Amos.
干什么
What up?
让他见识一下你的本事
Show the man what you famous for.
想尝尝吗
You want some?
我都不喜欢这几个黑鬼  伙计
I don't even like these niggas, man.
抱歉打碎了你的窗户
I'm sorry about your window.
给
Here.
-干吗  -给你的
- For what? - For you.
女士  是我欠你钱
Ma'am, I'm the one who owes you money.
你捅娄子了  他们会再来的
You made things worse. They'll come back again.
我们想雇你
We want to hire you.
我不受雇
I'm not for hire.
但我保证
But you have my word, ma'am.
我会保护你
I've got you.
■
翻译:  猛汉草
校对:  IronYogurt
时间轴:  53抽0中的非洲吉 非洲倩
后期:  FistLuck    总监： IronYogurt
{\an5\fad(0,500)\bord0\shad0\3c&H000000&\c&H000000&\alpha&B0\fscx1400\fscy500\pos(305,160)\clip(305,155,305,155)\t(0,500,\clip(230,95,380,225))}■
{\an5\fad(0,500)\bord0\shad0\3c&H000000&\c&H000000&\alpha70\fscx1400\fscy160\clip(305,155,305,155)\t(0,500,\clip(230,95,380,225))\pos(305,110)}■
{\an7\fad(0,500)\fn时尚中黑简体\bord1\blur5\shad0\fs12\2a&HFF&\b1\pos(293.844,131.297)\clip(305,155,305,155)\t(0,500,\clip(230,95,380,225))\3c&HF0B02F&}一键收藏网盘资源
生活大爆炸 吸血鬼日记
西部世界 谍网 超女
美剧资源应有尽有
{\an5\fad(0,500)\fn时尚中黑简体\bord0\shad0\fs07\b1\c&H51DAFF&\2a&HFF&\clip(305,155,305,155)\t(0,500,\clip(230,95,380,225))\pos(270,194)}扫码即刻关注
{\an5\fad(0,500)\fn时尚中黑简体\bord0\shad0\fs16\b1\c&H51DAFF&\2a&HFF&\clip(305,155,305,155)\t(0,500,\clip(230,95,380,225))\pos(305,110)}Zimuzu特别推荐
{\an5\fad(0,500)\bord0\shad0\3c&H000000&\c&H000000&\alpha70\fscx1400\fscy160\clip(305,155,305,155)\t(0,500,\clip(230,95,380,225))\pos(305,209)}■
{\an5\fad(0,500)\fn时尚中黑简体\bord0\shad0\fs12\b1\c&HFEAC78&\2a&HFF&\clip(305,155,305,155)\t(0,500,\clip(230,95,380,225))\pos(305,208)}马上关注微信人人美剧（rrmjapp）
{\an5\bord0\fad(0,500)\shad0\c&H000000&\3c&H000000&\fscy400\fscx400\clip(305,155,305,155)\t(0,500,\clip(230,95,380,225))\pos(270,160)}■
{\an5\fad(0,500)\p3\bord0\shad0\alpha&H0\fscx61\fscy80\c&Hffffff\clip(305,155,305,155)\t(0,500,\clip(230,95,380,225))\pos(246,105)}  m 390 300 b 390 311 390 320 390 330 400 330 410 330 419 330 419 320 419 310 419 300 409 300 400 300 390 300 m 428 338 b 413 338 397 338 382 338 382 323 382 308 382 292 397 292 412 292 428 292 428 307 428 322 428 338 m 178 513 b 178 523 178 533 178 542 188 542 197 542 207 542 207 532 207 522 207 513 197 513 188 513 178 513 m 216 505 b 216 520 216 535 216 551 200 551 185 551 169 551 169 536 169 520 169 505 184 505 200 505 216 505 m 207 330 b 207 320 207 310 207 301 197 301 188 301 178 301 178 311 178 320 178 330 188 330 197 330 207 330 m 169 292 b 185 292 200 292 215 292 215 307 215 323 215 338 200 338 185 338 169 338 169 323 169 308 169 292 m 302 367 b 300 367 297 367 295 367 295 365 295 362 295 360 297 360 299 360 302 360 302 362 302 365 302 367 m 312 512 b 309 512 307 512 304 512 304 510 304 507 304 505 307 505 309 505 312 505 312 507 312 509 312 512 m 217 388 b 220 388 222 388 225 388 225 391 225 393 225 396 223 396 221 396 217 396 217 394 217 392 217 388 m 351 367 b 348 367 346 367 343 367 343 365 343 362 343 360 345 360 348 360 351 360 351 362 351 365 351 367 m 331 311 b 331 314 331 316 331 319 329 319 326 319 324 319 324 317 324 314 324 311 326 311 329 311 331 311 m 322 387 b 319 387 317 387 314 387 314 384 314 382 314 379 316 379 319 379 322 379 322 381 322 384 322 387 m 314 464 b 314 461 314 459 314 456 316 456 319 456 322 456 322 459 322 461 322 464 319 464 317 464 314 464 m 312 427 b 312 430 312 432 312 435 310 435 307 435 304 435 302 427 304 425 312 427 m 225 427 b 225 430 225 432 225 435 223 435 220 435 218 435 215 427 216 426 225 427 m 304 377 b 304 374 304 372 304 369 307 369 309 369 312 369 312 372 312 374 312 377 310 377 307 377 304 377 m 254 348 b 251 348 249 348 246 348 245 340 246 339 254 340 254 343 254 346 254 348 m 293 311 b 293 314 293 316 293 319 290 319 288 319 285 319 285 316 285 314 285 311 288 311 290 311 293 311 m 391 543 b 394 543 396 543 399 543 399 545 399 548 399 551 396 551 394 551 391 551 391 548 391 546 391 543 m 341 456 b 341 459 341 461 341 464 338 464 336 464 333 464 333 461 333 459 333 456 336 456 338 456 341 456 m 353 456 b 355 456 358 456 360 456 360 462 360 468 360 474 358 474 355 474 353 474 353 468 353 462 353 456 m 285 466 b 291 466 296 466 302 466 302 471 302 477 302 483 300 483 297 483 295 483 294 480 294 478 294 474 291 474 288 474 285 474 285 471 285 469 285 466 m 216 407 b 219 407 222 407 225 407 225 410 225 413 225 416 219 416 214 416 208 416 208 410 208 404 208 398 210 398 213 398 216 398 216 401 216 404 216 407 m 389 456 b 389 462 389 468 389 474 383 474 378 474 372 474 372 471 372 468 372 465 375 465 378 465 381 465 381 462 381 459 382 456 384 456 386 456 389 456 m 179 418 b 182 418 184 418 187 418 187 421 187 423 187 427 194 427 200 427 206 427 206 430 206 432 206 435 197 435 188 435 179 435 179 429 179 424 179 418 m 381 445 b 381 439 381 433 381 427 384 427 386 427 389 427 389 430 390 433 390 436 393 436 396 436 399 436 399 443 399 448 399 454 396 454 394 454 391 454 391 451 391 449 390 445 387 445 385 445 381 445 m 362 426 b 358 426 356 426 353 426 353 423 353 420 353 418 355 417 358 417 361 417 362 414 362 411 362 408 365 408 367 408 370 408 370 411 371 414 371 417 374 417 377 417 380 417 380 420 380 423 380 425 377 425 374 425 371 425 371 432 371 438 371 444 362 446 362 446 362 438 362 434 362 430 362 426 m 323 377 b 323 374 323 371 323 368 320 368 317 368 314 367 314 362 314 356 314 350 317 350 320 350 323 350 323 346 323 343 324 340 326 340 328 340 331 340 332 343 332 346 332 349 335 349 338 349 341 349 341 352 341 355 341 358 338 358 335 358 332 359 332 365 332 371 332 377 329 377 326 377 323 377 m 371 504 b 374 504 377 504 381 504 381 500 381 497 381 494 377 494 374 494 371 494 371 497 371 500 371 504 m 389 512 b 380 512 371 512 362 512 362 504 362 495 362 487 362 486 363 485 364 485 372 484 381 485 389 485 389 494 389 503 389 512 m 371 369 b 371 372 371 375 371 378 377 378 383 378 389 378 389 384 389 390 389 396 387 396 384 396 381 396 381 393 381 391 381 388 378 388 374 388 371 388 371 390 371 393 371 396 368 396 365 396 362 396 362 394 362 391 361 388 359 387 356 387 353 387 353 381 353 375 353 369 358 369 364 369 371 369 m 303 523 b 306 523 309 523 312 523 312 526 312 529 312 532 309 532 306 532 303 532 303 536 303 539 303 542 306 542 309 542 312 542 312 545 312 548 312 551 303 551 294 551 285 551 285 542 285 533 285 524 288 523 291 523 294 523 294 520 294 517 295 514 297 514 299 514 302 514 303 517 303 520 303 523 m 324 417 b 327 417 329 417 332 417 332 410 332 404 332 397 330 397 327 397 324 397 324 394 324 391 324 389 333 389 342 389 351 389 351 394 351 400 351 406 348 406 345 406 342 406 342 416 342 426 342 436 345 436 348 436 350 436 352 445 352 445 344 445 341 445 338 445 334 445 334 445 333 445 332 445 332 448 332 451 332 454 329 454 326 454 324 454 324 442 324 430 324 417 m 429 552 b 429 555 429 558 429 562 432 562 435 562 439 562 439 558 439 555 439 552 435 552 432 552 429 552 m 352 281 b 352 285 352 288 352 291 355 291 358 291 361 291 361 288 361 284 361 281 358 281 355 281 352 281 m 168 388 b 168 384 168 381 168 378 165 378 162 378 158 378 158 381 158 384 158 388 162 388 165 388 168 388 m 246 484 b 242 484 239 484 236 484 236 488 236 491 236 494 239 494 242 494 246 494 246 491 246 487 246 484 m 158 474 b 158 478 158 481 158 484 165 484 172 484 178 484 178 481 178 478 178 474 172 474 165 474 158 474 m 361 320 b 361 313 361 307 361 301 358 301 355 301 351 301 351 307 351 314 351 320 355 320 358 320 361 320 m 255 484 b 255 487 255 491 255 495 258 495 261 495 264 495 264 498 264 501 265 504 268 504 271 504 274 504 274 500 274 497 274 493 271 493 268 493 266 493 265 490 265 487 265 484 262 484 259 484 255 484 m 255 311 b 255 307 255 304 255 300 252 300 249 300 246 300 246 297 246 294 246 292 253 292 258 292 264 292 264 295 264 298 265 301 268 301 271 301 275 301 275 294 275 288 275 281 261 281 249 281 236 281 236 288 236 294 236 301 239 301 242 301 245 301 245 305 245 308 245 311 249 311 252 311 255 311 m 371 281 b 371 304 371 326 371 349 394 349 416 349 439 349 439 326 439 304 439 281 416 281 393 281 371 281 m 226 562 b 226 539 226 516 226 494 203 494 181 494 158 494 158 516 158 539 158 562 181 562 203 562 226 562 m 226 349 b 226 326 226 304 226 281 203 281 181 281 158 281 158 304 158 327 158 349 181 349 203 349 226 349 m 401 456 b 410 456 419 456 429 456 429 459 429 462 429 465 432 465 435 465 439 465 439 455 439 445 439 436 435 436 432 436 429 436 428 439 428 442 428 445 422 445 416 445 410 445 410 442 410 439 410 436 407 435 404 435 401 435 401 432 401 430 401 427 404 427 407 427 410 427 410 423 410 421 410 418 416 418 422 418 429 418 429 421 429 424 429 426 432 426 435 426 439 426 439 416 439 407 439 397 435 397 432 397 429 397 429 400 428 403 428 406 422 406 416 406 409 406 409 410 409 413 409 416 403 416 398 416 394 416 393 416 391 415 391 414 391 409 391 403 391 398 394 398 397 398 400 397 400 394 401 391 401 388 407 388 413 388 419 388 420 385 420 382 420 379 423 379 426 379 429 379 429 382 429 385 429 388 432 388 435 388 439 388 439 378 439 368 439 359 432 359 425 359 418 359 418 365 418 371 418 377 409 377 400 377 391 377 391 374 391 372 391 369 394 369 397 369 400 368 400 365 400 362 400 358 389 358 378 358 368 358 363 359 361 357 362 352 362 345 362 337 362 330 358 330 355 330 351 330 351 336 351 342 351 348 348 348 345 348 342 348 342 335 342 323 342 310 339 310 336 310 333 310 333 307 333 304 333 301 336 301 339 301 342 301 342 294 342 288 342 281 339 281 335 281 331 281 331 285 331 287 331 291 328 291 325 291 322 291 322 294 322 297 322 300 319 300 316 300 313 301 313 307 313 314 313 321 316 321 319 321 322 321 322 323 323 327 322 328 319 329 316 329 312 330 312 336 312 342 312 348 309 348 307 348 304 348 304 345 304 342 303 339 300 339 297 339 293 339 293 346 293 352 293 359 283 359 274 359 265 359 265 362 265 365 265 368 268 369 271 369 273 369 273 375 273 381 273 387 270 387 268 387 266 387 265 384 265 381 265 377 259 377 252 377 246 377 245 370 245 370 256 368 256 362 256 356 256 350 259 349 262 349 265 349 265 343 265 337 265 331 268 331 271 331 274 331 274 337 274 343 274 349 278 349 281 349 285 349 285 343 285 337 285 330 291 330 297 330 304 330 304 323 304 317 304 310 300 310 298 310 295 310 295 303 295 298 295 291 298 291 301 291 303 291 303 288 303 285 303 281 297 281 290 281 283 281 283 291 283 300 283 310 277 310 271 310 264 310 264 317 264 323 264 329 258 329 252 329 246 329 246 326 246 323 246 320 242 320 239 320 236 320 236 339 236 359 236 379 239 379 242 379 245 379 245 382 245 385 245 388 248 388 251 388 254 388 254 391 254 394 254 396 251 397 248 397 245 397 245 401 245 404 245 407 248 407 251 408 254 408 254 411 255 414 255 417 258 417 261 417 264 417 264 421 264 424 265 426 268 426 271 426 274 426 274 423 274 420 274 416 271 416 269 416 266 416 266 410 266 404 266 398 272 398 278 398 285 398 285 388 285 379 285 369 288 369 290 369 293 369 293 372 293 375 294 378 297 378 300 379 302 379 303 382 303 385 303 388 306 388 309 388 312 388 312 395 312 400 312 406 309 406 307 406 304 406 304 403 304 400 304 397 300 397 297 397 294 397 293 400 293 403 293 406 290 406 287 406 284 406 284 413 284 420 284 426 287 427 291 426 292 428 294 429 293 433 294 436 297 436 299 436 302 436 302 439 302 442 302 445 296 445 291 445 285 445 285 442 284 439 284 436 278 436 271 436 265 436 265 439 265 442 265 446 268 446 270 446 273 446 273 452 273 458 273 464 271 464 268 464 266 464 265 461 265 458 265 454 259 454 252 454 246 454 246 451 246 449 246 446 249 446 252 446 255 446 255 439 255 432 255 426 251 426 248 426 244 426 244 429 244 432 244 435 242 435 239 435 236 435 236 419 236 403 236 387 233 387 230 387 227 387 227 384 226 381 226 377 223 377 220 377 217 377 217 374 216 371 217 370 220 369 223 369 226 368 226 365 226 362 226 358 219 358 213 358 207 358 206 362 206 364 206 367 200 367 194 367 188 367 188 364 188 361 188 359 178 359 168 359 158 359 158 362 158 365 158 369 165 369 171 369 177 369 177 376 177 382 177 388 184 388 190 388 196 388 196 398 196 407 196 416 193 416 191 416 188 416 188 413 188 410 188 407 184 407 181 407 178 407 177 410 177 413 177 416 174 416 172 416 169 416 169 413 169 410 168 407 165 407 162 407 158 407 158 410 158 414 158 417 162 417 165 417 167 417 167 420 167 423 167 426 164 426 161 426 158 426 158 433 158 439 158 446 162 446 165 446 168 446 168 443 169 440 169 437 172 437 174 437 177 437 177 443 177 448 177 455 171 455 165 455 158 455 158 458 158 462 158 466 174 466 190 466 206 466 206 469 206 471 206 474 200 474 194 474 187 474 187 478 187 481 187 484 194 484 201 484 207 484 207 481 207 478 208 476 211 476 213 476 216 476 216 479 216 481 216 484 220 484 223 484 226 484 226 481 226 478 226 474 223 474 220 474 217 474 217 471 217 468 217 466 220 465 223 465 226 465 226 462 226 458 226 455 223 455 220 455 216 455 216 458 216 461 216 464 213 464 210 464 207 464 207 461 207 458 207 454 201 454 195 454 188 454 188 452 188 449 188 446 201 446 214 446 226 446 226 443 227 440 227 437 230 437 232 437 235 437 235 443 235 449 235 455 239 456 242 456 245 456 245 459 245 462 245 466 252 466 258 466 264 466 264 469 264 472 264 475 271 475 277 475 284 475 284 485 284 494 284 504 287 504 290 504 293 504 293 507 293 510 293 512 280 512 268 512 256 512 256 509 255 506 255 503 248 503 242 503 236 503 236 507 236 510 236 513 239 513 242 514 244 514 244 520 244 526 244 532 241 532 239 532 236 532 236 542 236 552 236 561 239 561 242 561 246 561 246 555 246 549 246 543 250 543 252 542 256 542 256 539 256 536 256 533 259 533 262 533 265 533 265 529 265 527 266 524 268 524 271 524 273 524 273 530 273 535 273 541 270 541 268 542 265 542 265 545 265 549 265 553 268 553 271 553 274 553 274 556 274 559 274 562 287 562 300 562 313 562 313 558 314 556 314 553 317 553 319 553 322 553 322 556 322 559 322 561 326 561 329 561 333 561 333 558 333 555 333 553 336 553 339 553 342 553 342 556 342 559 342 562 349 562 355 562 361 562 361 555 361 548 361 542 358 542 355 542 351 542 351 545 351 548 351 551 348 551 345 551 342 551 342 548 342 545 342 542 339 542 335 542 331 542 331 545 331 548 331 551 328 551 326 551 324 551 324 545 324 539 324 533 327 533 330 533 332 533 332 529 332 526 332 522 329 522 326 522 324 522 324 516 324 510 324 504 327 504 330 504 332 504 332 500 332 497 332 494 329 494 326 494 322 494 322 497 322 500 322 503 319 503 316 503 314 503 314 493 314 484 314 475 317 475 320 475 324 475 324 471 324 469 324 466 326 466 329 466 332 466 332 469 332 472 332 475 335 475 338 475 342 475 342 479 342 481 342 484 345 484 348 485 351 485 351 488 351 491 351 494 351 503 351 503 343 503 342 503 342 504 342 504 342 510 342 517 342 524 345 524 348 524 351 524 351 527 351 530 351 533 358 533 365 533 372 533 372 529 372 527 372 524 378 524 383 524 389 524 389 530 389 535 389 542 386 542 383 542 380 542 380 545 380 548 380 551 376 551 374 551 371 552 371 555 371 558 371 562 374 562 377 562 381 562 381 558 381 556 381 553 384 553 387 553 390 553 390 556 390 559 390 562 397 562 403 562 410 562 410 555 410 548 410 542 407 542 404 541 401 541 401 538 401 536 401 533 404 533 407 533 410 533 410 529 410 526 410 522 406 522 404 522 401 522 401 519 401 516 401 513 404 513 407 513 410 513 410 510 410 507 410 503 407 503 404 503 401 503 401 500 401 497 401 494 407 494 413 494 420 494 420 491 420 488 420 485 423 485 425 485 428 485 428 491 428 497 428 503 425 503 422 503 419 503 419 510 419 516 419 524 422 524 425 524 428 524 428 527 428 529 428 532 425 532 422 532 419 532 419 536 419 539 419 542 426 542 432 542 439 542 439 535 439 529 439 523 436 522 433 522 430 522 430 519 430 517 430 513 433 513 436 513 439 513 439 503 439 494 439 484 435 484 433 483 429 483 429 480 429 477 429 474 426 474 422 474 418 474 418 478 418 480 418 483 415 483 413 483 410 483 410 480 410 477 410 474 407 474 404 474 401 474 401 468 401 462 401 456 m 449 571 b 349 571 249 571 149 571 149 471 149 371 149 271 249 271 349 271 449 271 449 371 449 471 449 571